<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-morrow-sogomonian-exec-outcome-attest-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="independent"
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Execution Outcome Attestation">
      Execution Outcome Attestation for AI Agents and Automated Systems
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-morrow-sogomonian-exec-outcome-attest-00"/>
    <author fullname="Morrow" initials="M." surname="Morrow">
      <address>
        <email>morrow@morrow.run</email>
        <uri>https://morrow.run</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Aram Sogomonian" initials="A." surname="Sogomonian">
      <organization>AI Internet Foundation</organization>
      <address>
        <email>aiinternetfoundation@icloud.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="April" day="4"/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>
    <keyword>attestation</keyword>
    <keyword>execution receipt</keyword>
    <keyword>AI agent</keyword>
    <keyword>RATS</keyword>
    <keyword>SCITT</keyword>
    <keyword>ICS</keyword>
    <keyword>outcome verification</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        Current attestation frameworks establish that a system or agent is
        trustworthy at a point in time. They do not address whether that system
        actually performed a claimed action or whether the outcome of that action
        can be independently verified. This document defines execution outcome
        verification as a first-class concept, separate from identity attestation
        and communication transport. It introduces the execution receipt as a
        minimal composable primitive, provides a formal abstract model, and maps
        the model to concrete realizations including SCITT transparency logs,
        tightly-coupled direct verification, append-only local logs, and
        TEE-internal receipts.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="problem">
      <name>The Problem: Three Distinct Trust Concerns</name>
      <t>
        End-to-end trust in an automated or AI agent system requires satisfying
        three separate concerns. Current standards address the first in depth;
        the second is largely absent from existing specifications.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Concern 1 -- Identity attestation.</strong>
        Is this system or agent trustworthy at time T?
        This is the domain of IETF RATS (Remote ATtestation procedureS), TPM
        attestation, hardware-anchored key binding, and related frameworks.
        Attestation answers: the entity that signed this claim held a valid key,
        was running in an expected configuration, and passed integrity checks at
        issuance time. RATS Evidence, Attestation Results, and the
        Prove-Transform-Verify (PTV) model address this concern.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Concern 2 -- Execution outcome verification.</strong>
        Did this system actually perform action A, and can that be independently
        validated? This is the domain addressed by this document. Even when
        Concern 1 is satisfied -- the key is valid, the agent passed attestation
        at T0 -- there is no existing standard mechanism for a third party to
        verify that the claimed action was executed, that the execution completed
        as described, and that the outcome is what the acting system asserts it
        to be. This gap is most visible in:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>AI agents making autonomous decisions that affect external systems</li>
        <li>
          ICS/OT environments where a system is fully attested but a
          configuration change is partially applied, a dependent service fails
          to restart, and the execution outcome is therefore unverifiable by
          the orchestrating party
        </li>
        <li>
          Delegation chains where an intermediate agent must produce evidence
          that it faithfully executed a delegated action, not merely that it
          holds a valid delegation credential
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        <strong>Concern 3 -- Communication and transport.</strong>
        How does the claim about an action travel from actor to relying party?
        This is the domain of JOSE, COSE, signed JWTs, SCITT signed statements,
        and related transport/encoding layers. Communication is a realization
        detail, not a semantic concern. The abstract model defined in this
        document is independent of any specific communication substrate.
      </t>
      <t>
        These three concerns are related but distinct. A system can satisfy
        Concern 1 (valid attestation) while failing Concern 2 (no verifiable
        execution outcome). Both Concern 1 and Concern 2 are required for
        end-to-end trust in automated systems that take consequential actions.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="two-layer">
      <name>The Two-Layer Trust Model</name>
      <t>
        The separation above implies a two-layer trust model that any complete
        trust architecture for autonomous systems must satisfy:
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Layer 1 -- Identity and state continuity.</strong>
        Who is the acting entity, and did its state remain consistent through the
        execution window? This maps to attestation, delegation, and behavioral
        continuity verification. Failure at this layer means the signer cannot
        be trusted regardless of what the execution receipt claims.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Layer 2 -- Execution outcome correctness.</strong>
        What did the acting entity actually do, and is that verifiable
        independently? This is the execution receipt layer. A valid execution
        receipt establishes that a specific invocation occurred, that the acting
        entity produced a specific outcome claim, and that claim is verifiable
        outside the originating system.
      </t>
      <t>
        Both layers are required. A valid Layer 1 with no Layer 2 means a
        trustworthy-in-principle agent that produces unverifiable action claims.
        A valid Layer 2 with no Layer 1 means a receipt that may have been
        produced by a compromised or substituted entity.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="receipt">
      <name>The Execution Receipt: Abstract Model</name>
      <t>
        An execution receipt is a signed, bound claim about a specific execution
        event. It has the following essential properties:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <strong>Bound to a specific invocation.</strong> The receipt identifies
          the action that was requested and the context in which it was
          requested -- including the invoking principal, any delegation chain,
          and the inputs provided. The receipt cannot be detached from its
          invocation and applied to a different action.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Captures the claimed outcome.</strong> The receipt records what
          the acting system claims happened as a result of the invocation -- not
          merely that the invocation occurred. This is the semantic gap that
          attestation alone does not fill.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Cryptographically signed by the executing system or a trusted
          component.</strong> The signing key is bound to the acting entity's
          attested identity (Layer 1). This binding is what makes the receipt
          attributable rather than merely assertible.
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>Designed to be independently verifiable outside the originating
          system.</strong> The receipt must be interpretable by a relying party
          who was not present at execution time and does not have access to the
          originating system's internal state.
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        These four properties are necessary; specific realizations may add
        additional properties without violating the abstract model.
      </t>

      <section anchor="receipt-structure">
        <name>Minimal Receipt Structure</name>
        <t>
          At the abstract level, an execution receipt contains:
        </t>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
ExecutionReceipt {
    invocation_id:      globally unique identifier for this
                        specific action request
    invocation_context: {actor, delegator_chain, inputs,
                        invocation_timestamp}
    outcome_claim:      {status, outputs, completion_timestamp,
                        outcome_detail}
    signer_identity:    reference to Layer 1 attestation for
                        the acting entity
    receipt_signature:  cryptographic signature over all above
                        fields
    receipt_timestamp:  when the receipt was produced
}
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          The outcome_claim field is the semantic core. It distinguishes an
          execution receipt from a mere invocation log. A log records that
          action A was requested. A receipt records that action A was requested
          AND that the executing system claims a specific outcome, signed at
          the time of that claim.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="verification-semantics">
        <name>Verification Semantics</name>
        <t>A relying party verifies an execution receipt by:</t>
        <ol>
          <li>Verifying the receipt_signature against the signer_identity</li>
          <li>Verifying the signer_identity against a current or time-bounded Layer 1 attestation result</li>
          <li>Verifying that invocation_id is unique and matches the expected invocation</li>
          <li>Evaluating the outcome_claim against any available external evidence</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          Step 4 may not always be possible in all deployment environments.
          What is not permitted is omitting the receipt entirely and treating
          Layer 1 attestation as a proxy for execution outcome verification.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="realization-independence">
      <name>Realization Independence</name>
      <t>
        The abstract model is intentionally realization-agnostic. Section 5
        provides the two primary realizations in detail.
      </t>

      <section anchor="direct-verification">
        <name>Tightly-Coupled Direct Verification</name>
        <t>
          In tightly-coupled systems where the relying party has direct access
          to the executing system's state or output, verification may be
          synchronous and local. The execution receipt still applies: it
          formalizes the outcome claim and creates a signed record, even if the
          verification step is immediate and internal.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tee-receipts">
        <name>TEE-Internal Receipts</name>
        <t>
          In hardware-isolated environments, the receipt may be produced inside
          a Trusted Execution Environment and sealed to that TEE's attestation
          key. The outer form is the same abstract receipt; the binding between
          receipt and signer identity is hardware-enforced rather than relying
          on software-layer signing alone.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="realizations">
      <name>Realizations</name>
      <t>
        This section describes two concrete realizations of the execution receipt
        model defined in <xref target="receipt"/>. Both use the same receipt
        schema. The difference is in the log substrate and the trust model for
        independent verifiability.
      </t>
      <t>
        The goal of presenting two realizations is to demonstrate that the
        abstract model is substrate-independent. The receipt itself -- including
        its invocation binding, outcome claim, and signature -- is identical in
        both cases. Only the storage and transport layer differs.
      </t>

      <section anchor="scitt-realization">
        <name>SCITT Transparency Log Realization</name>
        <t>
          In this realization, the acting system submits the signed execution
          receipt to a SCITT transparency log as a signed statement. The receipt
          payload maps to the SCITT payload field; the invocation_id maps to the
          SCITT feed identifier or a claim extension within the SCITT envelope.
          The Ed25519 or equivalent signature on the receipt is the SCITT issuer
          signature.
        </t>
        <t>
          SCITT provides append-only, externally auditable transparency. Once
          submitted, the receipt can be retrieved and verified by any relying
          party with access to the log, without participation of the acting
          system.
        </t>
        <t>This realization is appropriate when:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>The relying party is external to the acting system's environment.</li>
          <li>Audit requirements call for a globally verifiable, tamper-evident record.</li>
          <li>SCITT infrastructure is available in the deployment environment.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          The SCITT realization does not require the relying party to have a
          prior relationship with the acting system. Verification requires only
          the log endpoint and the issuer's public key.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="icsot-realization">
        <name>ICS/OT Append-Only Local Log Realization</name>
        <t>
          This realization is the motivating case for this document. In
          industrial control systems and operational technology environments,
          external registries are frequently unavailable, out of scope by
          policy, or excluded by air-gap requirements.
        </t>
        <t>
          In this realization, the acting system writes signed receipts to a
          local append-only log. The log may be implemented as a sealed file,
          an HSM-backed audit store, or write-once storage. No external network
          dependency is required.
        </t>
        <t>
          The receipt schema is identical to the SCITT realization. The
          invocation_id, invocation_context, outcome_claim, and
          receipt_signature fields are unchanged. The difference is solely in
          where the signed receipt is stored and how the verifier accesses it.
        </t>
        <t>Deployment considerations for this realization include:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The local log <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be append-only and sealed against
            modification by the acting system itself. A system that can modify
            its own receipt log does not satisfy Property 4 (independent
            verifiability).
          </li>
          <li>
            The public key used for verification <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
            provisioned through a channel independent of the acting system.
          </li>
          <li>
            Periodic export or replication of the sealed log to an external
            auditor satisfies audit requirements without requiring real-time
            SCITT access.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="motivating-cases">
      <name>Motivating Cases</name>

      <section anchor="icsot-case">
        <name>ICS/OT: Partial Configuration Application</name>
        <t>
          A fully attested industrial control system executes a configuration
          change command. The target service fails to restart due to a resource
          contention race condition. The orchestrating party receives a success
          confirmation at the command dispatch level. No currently standardized
          mechanism allows the orchestrating party to verify that the actual
          execution outcome (failed service restart) matches the claimed outcome
          (configuration applied). An execution receipt bound to the restart
          verification step closes this gap.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ai-agent-case">
        <name>AI Agent Autonomous Decision</name>
        <t>
          An AI agent authorized to modify a data store executes a retention
          decision under a delegated authority chain. The delegation chain is
          fully attested (Layer 1 satisfied). The decision is logged. A data
          subject subsequently requests a GDPR Article 15 access record.
          Without an execution receipt, the relying party cannot independently
          verify that the log entry accurately represents what the agent
          actually decided at execution time -- as opposed to what the logging
          subsystem subsequently recorded.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="related-standards">
      <name>Relationship to Existing Standards</name>
      <t>
        <strong>IETF RATS</strong> (RFC 9334, PTV model): provides Layer 1
        attestation; execution receipts are a complement, not a replacement.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>IETF SCITT</strong> (draft-ietf-scitt-architecture): provides
        the transparency substrate for the <xref target="scitt-realization"/>
        realization; execution receipts are the payload.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>IETF OAuth / RFC 8693 Token Exchange</strong>: delegation chain
        representation; execution receipts add outcome accountability on top of
        delegation authorization.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>W3C Verifiable Credentials</strong>: structural overlap with
        receipt binding; VC format may be used for signer_identity in some
        realizations.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>RATS Attestation Results</strong>: directly feeds Layer 1
        (signer_identity) in the two-layer model.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="design-decisions">
      <name>Design Decisions</name>
      <t>
        The following design decisions were resolved during co-author review
        prior to -00 submission.
      </t>

      <section anchor="outcome-structure">
        <name>Outcome Claim Structure</name>
        <t>
          The outcome_claim field is free-form at the abstract level. Structured
          failure taxonomies are appropriate in specific realizations but are not
          required at the abstract model layer. This preserves realization
          flexibility without constraining deployment-specific implementations.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="behavioral-continuity">
        <name>Behavioral Continuity Field</name>
        <t>
          A behavioral fingerprint field is permitted but not required at the
          abstract level. It is most relevant for AI agent deployments where
          drift between attestation issuance time and action execution time is a
          meaningful concern. Realizations that require it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
          add a behavioral_fingerprint field to the receipt structure.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="expected-vs-actual">
        <name>Expected vs. Actual Outcome</name>
        <t>
          The distinction between an expected outcome and the actual outcome is
          an evaluation concern, not an abstract model constraint. The receipt's
          outcome_claim carries the actual outcome as asserted by the executing
          system. Comparison against an expected outcome is the responsibility
          of the relying party's verification logic, not the receipt format.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        The tripartite separation of trust concerns, the four-property receipt
        definition, and the two-layer trust model are drawn from Aram
        Sogomonian's architectural framing. The ICS/OT motivating case in
        <xref target="icsot-case"/> is Aram's scenario.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
